<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-05-29T13:26:51+07:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Hello World!</title><link href="/posts/hello-world" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hello World!" /><published>2022-05-29T00:00:00+07:00</published><updated>2022-05-29T00:00:00+07:00</updated><id>/posts/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="/posts/hello-world"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my blog’s first post!
<!--more--></p>

<p>I was working on my project the other day. I’m working on a desktop GUI project, which is not as popular as a web project nowadays. As a result, there are not that many online sources that I can refer to while working on it (not to mention the official documentation is not that good). So I was thinking, hey I should write this up so I can help my future self. While I’m at it I also think that writing it in a blog maybe is not a bad idea!</p>

<p>As you can see, my blog is a bit bare. I’m inspired by <a href="https://motherfuckingwebsite.com/">this website</a> for the design. Also, because it’s mainly just for my note I think it’s good to keep things simple and lightweight. Please let me know if you have any suggestions!</p>

<p>For now, I plan to write some posts related to desktop GUI software. More specifically on GTK and C. Please note that I’m not a professional C engineer by any means (I write java for a living, like your everyday software engineer). So, I’m sorry if most of my post only consists of surface-level knowledge or even contains any errors. Please let me know if that happened. You can send me an <a href="mailto:contact@matiasalvin.dev">email</a> or contact me on my socials.</p>

<p>So, as I’ve already mentioned. This blog will be mainly used as my notes on my software engineer journeys. Also, I’m not a native speaker. Hopefully, by writing a lot of English I can be better at my English. Thank you, and I hope you enjoy your stay here!</p>]]></content><author><name>mat</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to my blog’s first post!]]></summary></entry></feed>